RG 154:003, Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission
Connecticut State Library
Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission records
1972-2001
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission
4 cubic feet
The Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission was established when Governor William A. O'Neil issued Executive Order Number 15 on January 10, 1986. The Connecticut General Assembly in 1989 passed Public Act 89-258, "An Act Creating the Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission," to ensure the "commemoration of the birthday of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. in the state is meaningful and reflective of the spirit with which he lived and the struggles for which he died." The Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities is the secretariat for the holiday commission.
RG154_003
2011-078
Historical Note
United States Representative John Conyers introduced legislation four days after Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. death in 1968 for a national holiday. President Ronald Reagan signed Martin Luther King, Jr. Day into law on November 2, 1983. The first national celebration occurred on Januray 20, 1986.
Governor William A. O'Neil issued Executive Order Number 15 on January 10, 1986 creating the Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission with the Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities as its secretariat. The Connecticut General Assembly in 1989 passed Public Act 89-258, "An Act Creating the Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission," to ensure the "commemoration of the birthday of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. in the state is meaningful and reflective of the spirit with which he lived and the struggles for which he died." The commission is composed of nineteen appointed commissioners, who work to plan an annual celebration in honor of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., sponsor a youth conference and provide reports on activities in the state.
Scope and Content
The records were arranged into seven series which document the Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission. The series include Administrative Records, Correspondence, Subject Files, Press Files, Publications, Photographs, and Multimedia.
Series 1. Administrative Records, 1983-2001, consists of information on the commission and commissioners, meeting minutes and agenda, programs and proceedings for holiday celebrations, reports and surveys, youth activities and commissions in other states.
Series 2. Correspondence, 1986-1994, includes correspondence regarding activities sponsored by the commission, communciation between commissioners, information exchanged with commissioners from other states and correspondence with members of the Federal Holiday Commission.
Series 3. Subject Files, 1988-1989, consist of biographical sketches on Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Coretta Scott King as well as a copy of the Presidential Proclamation establishing Martin Luther King, Jr. Day as a federal holiday.
Series 4. Press Files, 1972-1992, contain clippings regarding civil rights or Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.
Series 5. Publications, 1986-1994, consist of reports, surveys, and printed material created by the commission or in support of annual activities. Planning and completed copies of the Freedom Trail poster and Connecticut brochure are included. Miscellaneous publications include catalogues, Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities mission statement and report, Klanwatch magazine, and playbills.
Series 6. Photographs, 1987-1991, includes reproduction photographs of Dr. King and Coretta Scott King, as well as photographs documenting holiday celebrations held in 1987 and 1991.
Series 7. Multimedia, 1988, contains a cassette tape of the 1988 Iowa Martin Luther King Celebration.
Arrangement
Series 1. Administrative Records, 1983-2001
Series 2. Correspondence, 1986-1994
Series 3. Subject Files, 1988-1989
Series 4. Press Files, 1972-1992
Series 5. Publications, 1986-1994
Series 6. Photographs, 1987-1991
Series 7. Multimedia, 1988
Restricted, 1989-1994
Index Terms
Subjects:
United States. Martin Luther King, Jr., Federal Holiday Commission -- Posters; Connecticut. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission; Connecticut -- Politics and government
Places:
Connecticut
Persons:
King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Green, Arthur L.; Borges, Francisco L.; King, Dennis J.; Martin, Louis
Document Types:
Brochures; Clippings; Correspondence; Minutes; Photographs; Posters; Press releases; Publications; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The records were transferred to the State Library in 2010.
Container List
- Series 1. Administrative Records, 1983-2001
  - Commission Meetings, Agenda and Attendance, 1986-1994
    - Administrative forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meeting schedules, agenda and attendance, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2-10)
  - Holiday Celebrations, 1987-2001
    - Connecticut Martin Luther King Conference, 1987, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. 25th anniversary commemoration, 1988 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - State celebration, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    - State celebration and correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
    - State celebration program, 1992-2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subject Files, 1983-1992
    - Budget, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Calendar for traveling photography exhibit "Hand in Hand for Justice", 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Commission appointments / resignations, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Commisioners, past, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Commissioners, present, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Connecticut Careers Trainee (CCT) position, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Federal law and Congressional transcript, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Liberty Bell history and celebration, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Substitute Senate Bill No. 506 - An Act Creating the Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Training Program for Common Care of Learning, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reports and Surveys, 1985-1994
    - 1990 survey and 1991 results, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Annual reports - Connecticut, 1989-1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Connecticut State Department of Education listing of enrollments by school and racial/ethnic status, 1985 October (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Surveys of city, town, and school programs and activities commemorating Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. birthday, 1986 December (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Survey of Connecticut labor law development in 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Youth Foundation, 1988-1994
    - Administrative, correspondence and 1994 Youth Conference attendance, 1988-1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Youth, 1997-2000
    - Youth conferences, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Commissions and Activities Outside of Connecticut, 1985-1992
    - Alaska, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Arizona, 1989 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Colorado, 1986 January 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - International Association of Official Human Rights Agencies (IAOHRA) King Commission, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Federal Commission reports, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Federal Holiday Commission National Information and Planning Conference, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Federal Holiday Commission National Planning Conference and correspondence, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Federal Holiday Commission National Planning Conference for State Holiday Commissions, 1986 July 18-20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Federal Holiday Commission publications and press releases, 1987-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - New Jersey, 1986 March 17 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - New York, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Rhode Island, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series 2. Correspondence, 1986-1994
  - Inbound and outbound correspondence, 1986-1994 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Series 3. Subject Files, 1988-1989
  - Biographies, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day Presidential Proclamation, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
- Series 4. Press Files, 1972-1992
  - Clippings, 1972-1988 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Clippings, 1989-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Press releases, 1985-1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series 5. Publications, 1986-1994
  - Brochure - Connecticut, circa 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Connecticut State Agency Description of Organization, Rules of Practice and Personal Data, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Freedom Trail posters and planning, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1991-1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Other brochures and posters, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series 6. Photographs, 1987-1991
  - Holiday Celebration, 1987
    - Arthur L. Green, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hopewell Concert Choir, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Hopewell Concert Choir, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Statue of Genius, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Arthur L. Green, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Governor William A. O"Neil, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Liberty Bell replica, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Hopewell Concert Choir, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - Unidentified, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
    - Arthur L. Green, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Liberty Bell replica, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
    - Governor William A. O"Neil, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Arthur L. Green, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Hopewell Concert Choir, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Holiday Celebration, 1991
    - ABCD Theater, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 23-27)
    - Hopewell Choir, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 28-30)
    - Unidentified, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 31-38)
    - Bell ringing, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 39-40)
    - Unidentified, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 41-45)
    - Negatives, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Portraits, undated
    - Dr. Martin Luther King standing behind a desk, undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Dr. Martin Luther King posing with chair, undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Portrait of Coretta Scott King, undated (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Series 7. Multimedia, 1988
  - Iowa Martin Luther King Celebration, 1 cassette tape, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Restricted, 1989-1994
  - Administrative Records - Subject Files
    - Commissioners, past, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Records - Youth Foundation
    - Administrative, correspondence and 1994 Youth Conference attendance, 1989-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)